<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Christian&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://www.jung-christian.de/tags/selinux/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Christian&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2017 by Christian Jung</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jung-christian.de/tags/selinux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>SELinux Compliance Policy</title>
      <link>http://www.jung-christian.de/post/2017/10/control-policy-selinux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 12:19:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jung-christian.de/post/2017/10/control-policy-selinux/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;compliance-policies&#34;&gt;Compliance Policies&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redhat.com/cloudforms&#34;&gt;CloudForms&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manageiq.org&#34;&gt;ManageIQ&lt;/a&gt; allow the definition of Compliance Policies which can be used to verify consistency of Virtual Machines, Instances, Hypervisors and other objects, in the entire environment. Compliance Policies can  trigger actions to be able to notify about non-compliance or to go one step further and enforce compliance, for example by using Ansible Playbooks to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of examples about Compliance Policies on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cloudformsblog.redhat.com/tag/compliance/&#34;&gt;official Red Hat CloudForms blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;adjust-the-smart-state-analysis-profile&#34;&gt;Adjust the Smart State Analysis Profile&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A separate blog post goes into details on how to &lt;a href=&#34;../modify-ssa-profile/&#34;&gt;create and modify a Smart State Analysis Profile&lt;/a&gt;. When creating the profile, it is important its name is &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; and the policy retrieves the content of the file /etc/sysconfig/selinux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;control-policies&#34;&gt;Control Policies&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policies in CloudForms and ManageIQ are always a combination of three items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Event: the event triggers the evaluation of the condition. An event can be something like &amp;ldquo;VM Power On&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Analysis completed&amp;rdquo; and many more. A list of out of the box events can be found by clicking on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explorer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and then clicking on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Events&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in the accordion on the left&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/list-of-events.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/list-of-events-300x96.png&#34; alt=&#34;out of the box events&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screenshot only shows a subset of all available events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Condition: the condition is evaluated after the specified event was detected. A condition can verify that a specific Operating System is installed, the VM configuration meets certain criteria and many more&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Action: after detecting the event and validating the condition, an action can be triggered. Actions can be specified differently if the condition was TRUE or FALSE. A Control Policy can can send an email alert, trigger a SNMP trap or any customized action. A number of actions are already shipped out of the box and can be found by clicking on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explorer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and then &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Actions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in the accordion on the left&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/list-of-actions.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/list-of-actions-300x95.png&#34; alt=&#34;list of actions&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screenshot only shows a subset of all available actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;compliance-policies-1&#34;&gt;Compliance Policies&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compliance policies are similar to Control Policies, but do not listen to events. To validate a Compliance Policy, the user can click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Policy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check Compliance of Last Known Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, or a Control Policy can trigger an Compliance Policy Check as an Action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compliance Policies can also mark the evaluated object as either Compliant or Non-Compliant. This information can also be used in Reports and Dashboards for a better overview or to be exported for further analysis. More information about Control and Compliance Policies can be found in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-us/red_hat_cloudforms/4.5/html/policies_and_profiles_guide/&#34;&gt;Policies and Profiles Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-a-compliance-policy-for-selinux&#34;&gt;Create a Compliance Policy for SELinux&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check if SELinux is in enforcing mode, a compliance policy like this can be used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Condition: analyse the content of /etc/sysconfig/selinux and verify &amp;ldquo;SELinux=enforcing&amp;rdquo; is found in the file&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Action: mark the VM as compliant or non-compliant&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of such a policy can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cbolz/ManageIQ/tree/master/control-policies&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;enable-the-policy&#34;&gt;Enable the Policy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable the Compliance Policy, it has to be part of a Policy Profile. The example found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cbolz/ManageIQ/tree/master/control-policies&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; is pre-configured accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one last step the Policy has to be enabled. This can be done on individual VMs or instances or any where in the hierarchy, up to the provider level. Policies are inherited to their child objects, for example if the Policy is enabled on a specific provider, it automatically applies to all objects found on this provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigate to the provider, e.g. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Compute&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Providers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the provider and click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Policy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manage Policies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/manage-policies.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/manage-policies-300x82.png&#34; alt=&#34;Manage Policies&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the box next to the Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/enable-policy-profile.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/enable-policy-profile-300x274.png&#34; alt=&#34;Enable Policy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Save&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The icon shows a yellow shield to illustrate the a Policy is enabled&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/provider-policy-enabled.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/provider-policy-enabled-300x77.png&#34; alt=&#34;Provider with enabled Policy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;verify&#34;&gt;Verify&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To verify the configuration, navigate to a VM or instances on the selected provider. Click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Perform SmartState Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Depending on the performance of the environment, this usually takes up to two minutes. In some environments it can also take much longer (in particular on OpenStack providers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Configuration of Smart State is out of scope for this document. There is a knowledge base article &lt;a href=&#34;https://access.redhat.com/articles/435283&#34;&gt;Virtual Machine SmartState Analysis Checklist&lt;/a&gt; with some useful links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System is not compliant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/system-non-compliant.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/system-non-compliant-300x58.png&#34; alt=&#34;System is not compliant&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System is compliant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/system-compliant.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jung-christian.de/images/system-compliant-300x61.png&#34; alt=&#34;System is not compliant&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SELinux Compliance Policy</title>
      <link>http://www.jung-christian.de/post/2017/11/continues-integration-with-automate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 12:19:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.jung-christian.de/post/2017/11/continues-integration-with-automate/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;continuous-integration-with-cloudforms-or-manageiq-automate&#34;&gt;Continuous Integration with CloudForms or ManageIQ Automate&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CloudForms and ManageIQ have an embedded editor which allows you to write and edit Automate code. This is convenient and easy to use for smaller modifications. As soon as you want to work on larger projects, you probably want more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;history: be able to go back to previous versions of your code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;branches: be able to create branches for test features or specific bug fixes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;better editor: the built in HTML editor is good enough for simple coding, but eventually you might want to use a more sophisticated editor. Popular editors amongst CloudForms users are Sublime, Atom, Visual Studio Code, or maybe just your optimized configuration of VI or Emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;logs: as soon as you collaborate working on Automate code, you want to be able to see how did which change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automate code can not only be written in the built in HTML editor, it can also be imported from a Git repository. For continuous integration, the REST API can be used to trigger a refresh every time new code is committed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-setup&#34;&gt;The setup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://gitlab.com&#34;&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt; are probably the most popular tools for Open Source Source Code Management tools currently used. The example below will work with either one of them, and should also work with any Git/CI combination, but might require some additional steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the example below, GitLab is used, since it has builtin CI/CD features. If you prefer GitHub, the following instructions should work as well, but you might need an additional tool, for example &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.travis-ci.org&#34;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/a&gt;, for the CI part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time new code is committed to the Git repository, a CI/CD Tool will detect that change and use an CloudForms API call to trigger a refresh. As a consequence, the script which is running on the CI/CD server must be able to open a TCP connection on port 443 to the CloudForms appliance by using its IP address or DNS name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;adding-a-git-repository&#34;&gt;Adding a Git repository&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create your Git repository with your Automate code. It is easier if you start with an existing repository, which actually already has some code checked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can add a Git repository, the necessary role has to be enabled. Click on the top right menu which shows your user name and then &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Make sure you enable the &amp;ldquo;Git Repositories Owner&amp;rdquo; role (you might have to scroll down to see all the roles, depending on your screen resolution).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;enable-git-repo-role.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/enable-git-repo-role-300x138.png&#34; alt=&#34;Enable Git Repositories Role&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can take a few moments for the services to start in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Import/Export&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. If the submit button is still greyed out, the role has not been activated yet. The question mark icon next to the submit button will give you an according hint. in this case wait another minute and reload the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From your Git repository, copy the HTML URL (SSH will not work). Paste the URL into the &amp;ldquo;Git URL&amp;rdquo; field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; A Git URL is pointing to a file with the suffix .git. For example, the Git URL for the repository used for this example is &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/cjung/automate.git&#34;&gt;https://gitlab.com/cjung/automate.git&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Username and Password are optional, as indicated in the UI. If you have a public repository on GitLab or GitHub, you will not need it. For private repositories, the user credentials have to be provided. CloudForms or ManageIQ will only need privileges to pull code, so a read only account is enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/git-repo-credentials.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/git-repo-credentials-300x285.png&#34; alt=&#34;Provide details for Git repository&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After clicking on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Submit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; it can take a few seconds before you see the next screen. During this delay, CloudForms/ManageIQ will try to access the repository and check if it can find an valid Automate repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If successful, the next screen will allow you to chose which tag or branch you want to checkout. For this example, we use the master branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/select-branch-or-tag-300x160.png&#34;&gt;1&lt;a href=&#34;images/select-branch-or-tag.png&#34;&gt;Select Branch or Tag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The import can once more take a few seconds, after which you should get a message, the import was successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;verify-the-new-automate-domain&#34;&gt;Verify the new Automate domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explorer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to see the domain after the import. Note that the domain is always read only. Code has to be changed in Git and can not be changed in the builtin editor anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/git-domain-300x65.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/git-domain.png&#34; alt=&#34;Automate Domain coming from Git&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After clicking on the Domain, a refresh can be initiated from the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; menu and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Refresh with new branch or tag&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This can also be used to change the branch or tag used to retrieve the code from Git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-a-locked-down-role&#34;&gt;Create a locked down role&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far we have manually imported Automate code from an existing Git repository. For a continuous integration workflow, we need an automatism to update the code in CloudForms, every time we commit a change to Git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be able to accomplish this, we need a user with the necessary privileges to refresh the Automate domain. This user has to log into CloudForms and perform a refresh by sending an API call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For security reasons, it is advised to create an account with restricted privileges. Fortunately CloudForms allows us to create a user which can only perform a refresh, but no other action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by clicking on your username on the top right corner and click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Access control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and open the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; menu and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Add a new Role&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Give the new role a name, for example &amp;ldquo;Git&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disable all privileges by making sure the box next to &amp;ldquo;Everything&amp;rdquo; is disabled&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drill into &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explorer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automate Domains&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modify&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and enable &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Refresh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/only-enable-automate-refresh-300x341.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/only-enable-automate-refresh.png&#34; alt=&#34;Only enable Automate Refresh privilege&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the new role&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groups&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Add a new Group&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enter a description, for example &amp;ldquo;Git&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the previously created role in the &amp;ldquo;Role&amp;rdquo; drop down list&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the parent tenant&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/add-git-group-300x159.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/add-git-group.png&#34; alt=&#34;Add the new group&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the new group&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, navigate to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Users&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Add a new User&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fill in the fields for &amp;ldquo;Full Name&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Username&amp;rdquo;, also set a password for the new user. Make sure to remember the username and password, since you will need both later. The email address is optional.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure to select the previously created group in the &amp;ldquo;Group&amp;rdquo; drop down list&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;images/add-git-user-300x259.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/add-git-user.png&#34; alt=&#34;Add the new user&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the new User.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;build-a-ci-pipeline&#34;&gt;Build a CI pipeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final piece in the puzzle is the script which is executed on the CI/CD server which triggers CloudForms to refresh the Automate domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gitlab&#34;&gt;GitLab&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example is using GitLab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;create a new file called &amp;ldquo;.gitlab-ci.yml&amp;rdquo; in the root directory of the git repository&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;add the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;job1:
  script:
    - curl -k -X POST -d&#39;{&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;refresh_from_source&amp;quot;}&#39; https://&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;password&amp;gt;@&amp;lt;FQDN or IP of CloudForms Appliance&amp;gt;/api/automate_domains/&amp;lt;name of Automate domain&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;travis-ci&#34;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;create a new file called &amp;ldquo;.travis.yml&amp;rdquo; in the root directory of the git repository&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;add the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;language: ruby

script:
- curl -k -X POST -d&#39;{&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;refresh_from_source&amp;quot;}&#39; https://&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;password&amp;gt;@&amp;lt;FQDN or IP of CloudForms Appliance&amp;gt;/api/automate_domains/&amp;lt;name of Automate domain&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;save the file and commit it to the repository&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;testing&#34;&gt;Testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After committing the build script, you can start doing changes to your Automate repository. Every time you commit a change, the build script should be executed and refresh the Automate domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that it can take a few seconds unless the CI/CD server detects the change and they show up in CloudForms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>